<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Building</title>
  <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>
<body>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Why use Imaging?">

<p>
  <ul>
      <li>This library is Free Software/Open Source. It is available under the <a href="license.html">Apache Software License</a>.</li>
      <li>Imaging is pure-Java. It will run on any jvm, on any platform without modification. It has no dependencies. Imaging only requires Java 1.4 or later.</li>
      <li>Imaging is easy to use. It has a simple, clean interface. Most operations are a single Imaging method call. See our Sample Code for examples.</li>
      <li>The core functionality is reading and writing a variety of image formats. See the list of Supported Formats.</li>
      <li>Imaging supports a number of format variations and uncommon features not supported by other image libraries.</li>
      <li>Imaging does more than read and write images. Reading image info (image size, colorspace, bit depth, etc.) and metadata is easy and does not require reading the entire image.</li>
      <li>Imaging supports reading and writing a variety of metadata in a structured way, including EXIF metadata.</li>
      <li>Imaging provides a consistent api across a variety of image formats.</li>
      <li>Imaging is network-aware. Imaging will only read the data it needs. Reading most image info and metadata only requires reading a header.</li>
      <li>Imaging was written with an eye to correctness and code clarity rather than efficiency.</li>
      <li>Imaging can extract and (simply) parse embedded ICC Profiles. Moreover, Imaging applies the icc profile by default, coverting read images to sRGB.
          This means images are color-corrected by default. see: 
          <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Color_Consortium">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Color_Consortium</a>, 
          <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SRGB">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SRGB</a>
      </li>
      <li>Imaging is actively maintained.</li>
  </ul>
</p>










</section>

</body>
</document>
